Guide to the Margaret Brenman-Gibson papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
- Series I: Research Files for Clifford Odets-American Playwright: The Years from 1906-1940, 1940-1999
  - Subseries I.10: Themes, 1959-1969
    - Family
      - 1964 (Box 13)
      - Pearl, 1963-1965 (Box 13)
      - L.J., 1964-1965 (Box 13)
      - Relatives, 1964-1965 (Box 13)
      - Comments, 1964-1965 (Box 13)
      - Nora and Walt, 1964-1965 (Box 13)
    - Identity Issues
      - 1964-1965 (Box 13)
      - Prophet Identity, 1964 (Box 13)
      - Writer, 1964 (Box 13)
      - Actor, 1964-1965 (Box 13)
      - Innocent, Honest Young Girl, 1964 (Box 13)
      - Jewishness, 1963-1965 (Box 13)
    - Past, 1963 (Box 13)
    - Playwrights and Playwriting, 1965-1966 (Box 13)
    - Psychoanalysis, 1965 (Box 13)
    - Relations to Others
      - 1964-1966 (Box 13)
      - Loyalty and Betrayal, 1964 (Box 13)
      - Others Image of Clifford Odets, 1964-1965 (Box 13)
      - Relation to Women, 1964-1965 (Box 13)
      - Children, undated (Box 13)
      - Relation to Men, 1963-1965 (Box 13)
    - Self-Advice, 1964 (Box 14)
    - Self-Image (Humility vs. Omnipotence), 1964-1965 (Box 14)
    - Sex, 1964-1965 (Box 14)
    - Success, 1963-1964 (Box 14)
    - Symbols, 1963-1965 (Box 14)
    - Values, 1963-1967 (Box 14)
    - Vignettes
      - 1964-1969, (3 folders) (Box 14)
      - Group Theatre, 1964-1968 (Box 14)
  - Subseries I.11: General Files, 1946-1999
    Subseries I.11: General Files is an assortment of files that did not fit in with the previous subseries. It consists of administrative and financial files, as well as logistics related to a trip that Brenman-Gibson took to California in 1965 to conduct research for her biography. There are two folders with material related to Odets' friend, Harold Clurman. Several files contain material from Virginia Rowe, who was both Odets' secretary, and later an assistant to Brenman-Gibson. Additionally, there are articles, clippings, notes, and notebooks. One of the notebooks is entitled, "Birdseye" and offers a broad summary of Odets' life.
    - Administration, 1963-1967 (Box 14)
    - Aftermath
      - 1965-1999, (2 folders) (Box 14)
      - Art from the Clifford Odets Estate, 1963-1965 (Box 14)
      - Clippings, 1965-1995 (Box 14)
      - Correspondence, 1964 (Box 14)
      - "Preface: A Memento"--Recollections of Clifford Odets by William Gibson, 1965 (Box 14)
      - Research Files, 1964 (Box 14)
    - Appendix
      - 1961, (2 folders) (Box 14)
      - Correspondence and Clippings (copy), 1958, (2 folders) (Box 14)
      - Notes and Other Materials, 1962-1965 undated (Box 14)
    - Articles, Clippings, Obituaries, 1963 (Box 14)
    - Birdseye--Notebook, undated, (3 folders) (Box 14)
    - Book Orders, 1964-1970 (Box 14)
    - California Trip
      - 1982 November (Box 14)
      - Addresses from Clifford Odets Phone Book, undated (Box 14)
      - Chronology, undated (Box 14)
      - Contacts
        - Brenman-Gibson, Margaret, 1965, (2 folders) (Box 14)
        - Penn, Peggy, 1965 (Box 14)
        - Rowe, Virginia, 1965 (Box 15)
      - Form Letters, 1965 (Box 15)
      - Information and Questions (Peggy Penn), undated (Box 15)
      - Organization, 1965 (Box 15)
    - Chapter One--Rough Draft, 1965-1978 (Box 15)
    - Chronological Files, 1962, (2 folders) (Box 15)
    - Clifford Odets: American Playwright--Notes, undated (Box 15)
    - Clurman, Harold, undated, (2 folders) (Box 15)
    - Expenses, 1963-1973 (Box 15)
    - Financials, 1977-1988, (2 folders) (Box 15)
    - Golden Boy--Assorted Material, 1962 (Box 15)
    - Notes, 1967-1988, (2 folders) (Box 15)
    - Notes for Article on Clifford Odets, undated (Box 15)
    - Odets, Clifford
      - Inventories, 1964, 1971, undated (Box 15)
      - Inventory of Notes and Papers, 1964 (Box 15)
      - Inventory of Papers, 1963 December 5 (Box 15)
    - The Odets Revival, A Humanist Hunger in America for Dialogue
      - Correspondence, 1972-1973 (Box 15)
      - Draft, 1972 (Box 15)
      - Typescript, 1972 (Box 15)
    - Reviews of Odets Works (includes some correspondence), 1982-1988 (Box 15)
    - Rowe, Virginia
      - Correspondence regarding Austin Riggs Move, 1976 (Box 15)
      - Notes, 1962-1973 undated (Box 15)
      - Screen Treatment on Clifford Odets, 1981 (Box 15)
      - The Show Must Go On--Notes, undated (Box 15)
      - "To Do" Notes (includes some correspondence from Luise Rainer, Maxwell Anderson), 1963-1966 (Box 15)
      - The Whispering Cup--Notes, 1946 (Box 15)
    - Sinatra, Frank--Superior Court of California, Odets v Sinatra, circa 1962 (Box 15)
    - TV Project with Dick Boone, 1962 (Box 15)
    - The Way West--Clippings, undated (Box 15)
    - Workbook, undated, (2 folders) (Box 15)
  - Subseries I.12: Rolodex
    Subseries I.12: Rolodex consists of Brenman-Gibson's rolodex of index cards. The index cards document the people with whom Brenman-Gibson conducted interviews as well as their correspondence.
    - Rolodex, undated (Box 18)
- Series II: Personal Correspondence, 1953-1993
  Series II: Personal Correspondence is a small series consisting of correspondence Margaret Brenman-Gibson had with Clifford Odets. It contains letters that Brenman-Gibson wrote to Odets, as well as the letters between her husband, William Gibson and Odets. There are original letters from Odets to Brenman-Gibson and her husband as well. Also included here is correspondence between the Gibson's and Odets' two children, Nora and Walt. The correspondence between Odets and the Gibson's ranges in date from 1953-1963, while the letters between the children is later from 1967-1993.
  - Brenman-Gibson, Margaret to Clifford Odets, 1953-1963, (2 folders) (Box 15)
  - Gibson, William to Clifford Odets, 1957-1962 (Box 15)
  - Odets, Clifford to Margaret Brenman-Gibson and William Gibson, 1953-1955 (Box 15)
  - Odets, Clifford to Margaret Brenman-Gibson and William Gibson, 1956-1963, (2 folders) (Box 16)
  - Odets, Nora, 1969-1993 (Box 16)
  - Odets, Walt, 1967-1986, (2 folders) (Box 16)
- Series III: Nuclear Weapons Activism, 1985-1987
  Series III: Nuclear Weapons Activism is a small series of material related to nuclear weapons activism that Brenman-Gibson engaged in during the 1980s. There are transcripts of interviews she did with two men: Peter Hagelstein and Lowell Wood. Additionally, there are audiocasettes of interviews she conducted with various people.
  - Interviews
    - Hagelstein, Peter, 1985-1987, (2 folders) (Box 16)
    - Wood, Lowell, 1985, (3 folders) (Box 16)
  - Audiocassettes, 1985 (Box 17a)
  - Audiocassettes, 1985 (Box 17b)
  - Audiocassettes, 1985 (Box 17c)